Guide to the S. S. Silver & Company Archive 1922-1957, undated (bulk 1946-1956) PR 61
New-York Historical Society
S. S. Silver & Company Archive
1922-1957, undated (Bulk 1946-1956)
New-York Historical Society
PR 61
9.5 Linear feet (16 boxes)
Photographs and some company documents from a Brooklyn-based interior design and store fixture company.
Provenance
Gift of Bertram S. Silver, 1982.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Historical Note
S. S. Silver & Company was formed in 1910 by Sol S. Silver (1885-1946). The company was located at 350-352 Butler Street in Brooklyn, and specialized in building and equipping commercial customers with new interior design displays. S. S. Silver & Company mainly dealt with businesses in the retail clothing trade, including specialty hat, shoe, and fabric stores as well as women's apparel. Among the other types of clientele served were restaurants, private residences, and business offices, primarily in Manhattan and Brooklyn.
Sol Silver died in 1946 while playing golf with his son, Bertram. Bertram S. Silver (1907-1999), who had been a vice-president in the company, subsequently became president of the firm. Under his leadership, S. S. Silver & Company began to expand the customer base, increasing both the geographical area and the size of the typical establishment served. Beginning in 1946, Silver & Co. won contracts to design the interiors for renovations at two major New York City department stores, Bergdorf Goodman and Saks Fifth Avenue. This led to further work designing displays and interiors for Saks Fifth Avenue's new stores in Beverly Hills, Chicago, and Detroit. The non-New York work attracted midwestern clients for Silver & Co., primarily larger department stores in Kansas City, Chicago, and Colorado Springs. Silver & Co. continued to be involved in smaller New York City-based store and office buildings and renovations.
Bertram Silver sought to raise the company's public profile by emphasizing publicity, writing many articles for trade publications, and advertising in the New York Times, among other periodicals. He emphasized a no-nonsense approach to retail design, one guaranteed to please his clients. In "Novelty Isn't Everything - Don't Overlook Prosaic," an article Silver wrote in June 1948 for Women's Wear Daily, he suggested that "â?¦ some of the more prosaic design elements, such as locking devices for fixtures, or thoughtfully-planned fitting rooms still can save headaches and make the difference in sales." Letters from satisfied clients (found in Series III) attest to their satisfaction with Silver & Co.'s design work.
In 1954, Bertram Silver moved from his West End Avenue apartment to a 65-acre estate in Newtown, Connecticut. S. S. Silver & Company was dissolved in 1960-1961. In 1968 Silver was named President and General Manager of the Lehigh and Leopold Division of Litton Industries.
Scope and Content Note
The S. S. Silver & Company Archive spans the period from 1922 to 1957, with most photographs dating from 1946 to 1956, when the company was led by Bertram S. Silver. The collection primarily contains photographs documenting the company's interior design work for retail companies. Photographs highlight the custom fixtures and office furniture, as well as the use of new technology (innovative lighting techniques, plexiglass partitions) that were the firm's strengths. Major photographers included are Joseph Molitor (1907-1996), an architectural photographer, and Ben Schnell, another photographer of interiors. The collection is divided into four series: Commercial Interiors; Residences; Company Records; and Publicity.
The majority of the collection consists of 8 x 10 inch photographs, generally black and white with some color, which are mounted on paper board. These were originally housed in thirty-nine numbered black binders, probably for publicity or archival purposes. However, photographs of the same store were not necessarily filed in the same binder, making it difficult to view all photos of one store at the same time. As the binders were not found to correspond to a chronological or other discernable order, the pages were disbound and filed alphabetically by store for ease of retrieval. Each page has been labeled on the verso with the original binder number and page number; a list of this original order also follows this finding aid. Three of the company's original binders have been saved and are housed at the end of the collection.
The collection also includes a folder of correspondence from satisfied clients, two scrapbooks of clippings and publicity material, and some early consultant reports on the company's structure and workflow. These materials document the inner workings and history of a commercial display and interior design firm.
Arrangement
Missing Title
Series I. Commercial Interiors
Series II. Residences
Series III. Company Records
Series IV. Publicity Scrapbooks
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
Other contemporaneous views of commercial interior design and display, as well as other photography by Ben Schnell, can by found in the Kim Hoffmann Photograph Collection (PR 077). The Bella C. Landauer Collection of Business and Advertising Ephemera (PR 031) also contains ephemera and publicity from department stores in New York City.
Manuals; Floor plans.; Photographic prints.; Trade catalogs; Scrapbooks.; Display of merchandise; Showrooms; Department stores -- United States.; Interior architecture; Office buildings -- Designs and plans.; Photograph albums.; Dwellings -- Interior views; Interiors.; New York (N.Y.); Correspondence.; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Detroit (Mich.); Kansas City (Mo.); Bergdorf Goodman (New York, N.Y.); Bernhard Ulmann Company; Kaufman's (Firm); Molitor, Joseph W.; S. M. Frank & Co.; Saks & Company (New York, N.Y.); Schnell, Ben; Silver, Sol S.; Woolf Brothers (Firm)
- Series I: Commercial Interiors
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I fills boxes 1 through 12 and forms the bulk of the collection. These photographs are all mounted on board, as described above, except for one folder of unmounted photographs of Bergdorf Goodman, and a spiral-bound notebook including a few photographs of a variety of stores. The Bergdorf photos are filed in with those from the albums. The notebook is filed at the end of the series.
  Bergdorf Goodman, Bernhard Ulmann, Kaufman's, S. M. Frank & Company, Saks Fifth Avenue, and Woolf Brothers are represented by the largest numbers of photographs. Architectural plans for the Bergdorf Goodman renovations are also included in this series. Color photographs were taken of the Detroit Saks Fifth Avenue and the Kansas City Woolf Brothers jobs; these are noted in the box listing.
  While most of the Silver & Co. work was for the garment trade, several other types of businesses are represented here. The offices of the law firm Strasser, Spiegelburg, Fried & Frank (now known as Fried, Frank) and the executive offices of Sterling Drug are represented. C & L Delicatessen, a midtown Manhattan restaurant, is also shown.
  In general, these photographs are stark shots meant to show the new interiors and display cases. People appear only in a few images of Bergdorf Goodman (before renovation). Publicity and clippings from Series IV, as well as correspondence from Series III, were used to provide dates from some of these photographs.
  The photographs are arranged alphabetically by company or store name, and then by city where necessary. The number of prints follows the name in parentheses.
  - A. & J. Engel, Inc. (4 prints) 18 East 50th Street, New York, NY, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    See also: Box 13, Folder 157
  - Addis Co. (3 prints) Syracuse, NY, 1944 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Adeline Shops (3 prints) 1018 Flatbush Avenue, Brooklyn, NY, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alexette Gloves (9 prints), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Alfreda, Inc (8 prints) 15 West 39th Street, New York, NY, 1946 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Arnold Constable (11 prints) Fifth Avenue at 40th Street, New York, NY, 1939 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Arthur Beir & Co. (9 prints) 57 Worth Street, New York, NY, 1939 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Automatic Manufacturing Co. (7 prints) Newark, N.J., undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - B. Blumenthal Co. (6 prints) 1372 Broadway, New York, NY, 1939 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bacmo Postman Corp. (7 prints) 244 Madison Avenue, New York, NY, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - Bergdorf Goodman, Perfume Department (2 prints) 746 Fifth Avenue, New York, NY, 1951-1956 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bergdorf Goodman, Shoe Department (3 prints) 746 Fifth Avenue, New York, NY, 1951-1956 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bergdorf Goodman, Sportswear Department (2 prints) 746 Fifth Avenue, New York, NY, 1951-1956 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bergdorf Goodman, Van Cleef & Arpels (2 prints) 746 Fifth Avenue, New York, NY, 1951-1956 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bergdorf Goodman, General (74 prints) 746 Fifth Avenue, New York, NY, 1951-1956 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 17-20)
  - Bergdorf Goodman, Architectural plans for alterations 746 Fifth Avenue, New York, NY, 1951-1956 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
  - The Bermuda Shop (2 prints) 545 Madison Ave, New York, NY, 1956 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
  - Bernhard Ulmann Co., Inc. (28 prints) 1150 Broadway, New York, NY, 1946-1947 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23-27)
  - Best & Co., Inc. (3rd floor) (6 prints) New York, NY, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 28)
  - Black, Starr & Gorham (8 prints) Millburn, NJ, 1956 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 29-30)
  - Black, Starr & Gorham (10 prints) New York, NY, 1930-1956 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 31-32)
  - Black, Starr & Gorham (6 prints) White Plains, NY, ca. 1948-1949 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 33)
  - C. & L. Delicatessen (10 prints) 2131 Broadway, New York, NY, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 34-35)
  - Cherie, Inc. (2 prints) 887 Sixth Avenue, New York, NY, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 36)
  - Christian Dior Shoes (1 print), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 36)
  - Collins & Aikman Corp. (7 prints) 200 Madison Avenue, New York, NY, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 37)
  - Crescent Corset Co. (5 prints), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 38)
  - Delman Shoe Salon (8 prints) Los Angeles, CA, 1957 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 39)
  - Delman Shoe Salon (1 print) New York, NY, 1956 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 39)
  - Dieges & Clust (3 prints) 17 John Street, New York, NY, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 40)
  - Dobbs (13 prints) 380 Park Avenue, New York, NY, 1928 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 41-42)
  - Ducharne Fabrics (11 prints) 244 Madison Avenue, New York, NY, 1945-1946 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 43-44)
  - E. T. Howard (6 prints) New York, NY, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 45)
  - Flah & Co. (5 prints) Syracuse, NY, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 46)
  - Fred Greenberg Dress Co. (5 prints) New York, NY, 1947 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 47)
  - Friedman's Shoe Store (5 prints) 1034 Flatbush Avenue, Brooklyn, NY (5 prints), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 48)
  - Friedman's Shoe Store (3 prints) 379 Knickerbocker Avenue, Brooklyn, NY, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 49)
  - Futura Sales Company (6 prints) 210 Madison Avenue, New York, NY, 1951 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 50)
  - General Shoe Corporation (6 prints) Empire State Building, New York, NY, 1956 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 51)
  - Georg Jensen (10 prints) 667 Fifth Avenue, New York, NY, 1946-1947 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 52-55)
  - Ground Gripper(1 print) 310 Livingston Street, Brooklyn, NY, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 54)
  - Hafner Associates (14 prints) New York, NY, 1946 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 55-57)
  - Hat Corporation of America (9 prints) 530 Fifth Avenue, New York, NY, 1957 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 58-59)
  - Hudson Finishing Corporation (5 prints) New York, NY, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 60)
  - I. B. Cohen & Sons (6 prints) New Rochelle, NY, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 61)
  - Ideal Novelty Toy Company (11 prints) New York, NY, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 62-63)
  - John B. Stetson Company (5 prints) 475 Fifth Avenue, New York, NY, 1954 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 64)
  - Julius Kayser & Co. (5 prints) 500 Fifth Avenue, New York, NY, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 65)
  - Kaufman's (31 prints) 27 South Tejon Street, Colorado Springs, CO, 1948 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 66-71)
  - Kenyon & Eckhardt Inc. (9 prints) New York, NY, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 72-73)
  - Knox the Hatter (4 prints) 452 Fifth Avenue, New York, NY, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 74)
  - Knox the Hatter (4 prints) 161 Broadway, New York, NY, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 75)
  - M. G. Peters & Bros. (4 prints) 480 Fulton Street, Brooklyn, NY, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 76)
  - Masback Hardware (4 prints) 326 Hudson Street, New York, NY, 1936 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 77)
  - Monique Bag Company (3 prints) 745 Fifth Avenue, New York, NY, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 78)
  - Munsingwear, Inc. (3 prints) New York, NY, 1947 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 79)
  - Nat Lewis (9 prints) 1637 Broadway, New York, NY, before 1947 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 80-81)
  - National Fabrics Corporation (27 prints) 1071 Sixth Avenue, New York, NY, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 82-86)
  - Physical Culture Shoe Store (3 prints) 2398 Broadway, New York, NY, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder unknown container)
  - Remond-Holland (9 prints) 244 Madison Avenue, New York, NY, 1946 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 88-89)
  - Rhealee Hat Shop (6 prints) 408 Fifth Avenue, New York, NY, 1940 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 90)
  - Rollins Company (13 prints) Detroit, MI, 1947-1948 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 91-93)
  - S. M. Frank & Company, Inc. (9 prints) 2 East 54th Street, New York, NY, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 94-95)
  - S. M. Frank & Company, Inc.(15 prints) 18 East 54th Street, New York, NY, undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 96-98)
  - Saks Fifth Avenue (9 prints) Beverly Hills, CA, 1947 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 99-100)
  - Saks Fifth Avenue (7 prints) Chicago, IL, undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 101-102)
  - Saks Fifth Avenue, Men's Shop (19 prints) Detroit, MI, 1946-1949 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 103-106)
  - Saks Fifth Avenue, Antoine Salon (16 prints) Detroit, MI, 1946-1949 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 107-109)
  - Saks Fifth Avenue, Antoine Salon (cont.)(15 prints) Detroit, MI, 1946-1949 (Offsite-box 8, Folder unknown container)
  - Saks Fifth Avenue, General (31 prints) Detroit, MI, 1946-1949 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 110-115)
  - Saks Fifth Avenue, General (color photographs) (21 prints) Detroit, MI, 1946-1949 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 116-119)
  - Saks Fifth Avenue, General (color photographs) (cont.) (9 prints) Detroit, MI, 1946-1949 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 120-121)
  - Saks Fifth Avenue, Fabrics Salon (8 prints) New York, NY, 1943 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 122)
  - Saks Fifth Avenue, Jewelry Salon (4 prints) New York, NY, 1946 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 123)
  - Seal Sac, Inc. (6 prints) 6 East 39th Street, New York, NY, undated (Offsite-box 10, Folder 124)
  - Sterling Drug (7 prints) 1450 Broadway, New York, NY, 1951-1952 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 125)
  - Store Modernization Exhibit (1 print) Grand Central Palace, New York, NY, 1947 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 126)
  - Strasser, Spiegelburg, Fried & Frank (3 prints) New York, NY, undated (Offsite-box 10, Folder 126)
  - Treo Corset Company (13 prints) 200 Madison Avenue, New York, NY, 1950 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 127-129)
  - Wamsutta Mills (8 prints) Empire State Building, New York, NY, 1951 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 130-131)
  - Wimmelbacher & Rice (8 prints) 244 Madison Avenue, New York, NY, undated (Offsite-box 11, Folder 132-133)
  - Wm. Hahn & Company (1 print) 414 Ninth Street, Washington, DC, 1922 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 134)
  - Woolf Brothers, Before Renovation (4 prints) Wichita, KS, 1948 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 135)
  - Woolf Brothers, After Renovation (33 prints) Wichita, KS, 1948 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 136-141)
  - Woolf Brothers, Model of First Floor (10 prints) Kansas City, MO, 1947-1949 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 142-143)
  - Woolf Brothers, Second Floor Before and After Renovation (5 prints) Kansas City, MO, 1947-1949 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 144)
  - Woolf Brothers, Third Floor Before Renovation (4 prints) Kansas City, MO, 1947-1949 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 145)
  - Woolf Brothers, Shoe Department (5 prints) Kansas City, MO, 1947-1949 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 146)
  - Woolf Brothers, Exterior Views (3 prints) Kansas City, MO, 1947-1949 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 147)
  - Woolf Brothers, General (30 prints) Kansas City, MO, 1947-1949 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 148-155)
  - Woolf Brothers, General (color photographs) (5 prints) Kansas City, MO, 1947-1949 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 156)
  - Notebook with assorted photographs includes: A & J Engel Inc., Alfreda Inc., Nat Lewis, Rollins Company, Woolf Brothers, Wichita and Kansas City, 1947-1949 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 157)
  - Three empty binders (Box Unknown container 745 for instance of Three empty binders, Folder unknown container)
    See: Box 16
- Series II: Residences
  Series II includes several interior images of four different homes. One is Sol S. Silver's residence on West End Avenue. Another belongs to Saul Brodsky, who was a business, and perhaps social, acquaintance of Silver. These images are all undated.
  Photographs are filed alphabetically by inhabitant.
  - Brodsky, Saul, Residence (5 prints), undated (Offsite-box 13, Folder 158)
  - Dreitzer, Albert J., Residence (6 prints), undated (Offsite-box 13, Folder 159)
  - Lipson Residence (5 prints), undated (Offsite-box 13, Folder 160)
  - Silver, Sol S., Residence (3 prints) 336 West End Avenue, New York, NY, undated (Offsite-box 13, Folder 161)
- Series III: Company Records and Correspondence
  Series III spans the years from 1922 to 1954 and consists largely of letters from satisfied customers, some of which were used as publicity by Silver & Co. The series also includes a 1922 report from Raymond Bell Consulting on the organization of Silver & Co., a 1923 report from Cooley & Marvin Co. about a proposed rearrangement of Silver's manufacturing equipment; and a 1946 Silver Company manual.
  - Report from Raymond Bell Consulting, 1922 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 162)
  - Report from Cooley & Marvin Co., 1923 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 163)
  - Company Manual, 1946 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 164)
  - Correspondence, Letters of Reference, 1922-1954 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 165)
- Series IV: Publicity Scrapbooks
  Series IV. Publicity Scrapbooks contains two scrapbooks made with black kraft paper and post bindings. Newspaper and magazine clippings are pasted to each page, or are laid in to the scrapbook pages. Scrapbook One spans the years 1931 to 1952 and includes a variety of Silver & Company flyers, advertisements, specifications for potential customers, and newspaper and trade journal clippings. Publications such as Women's Wear Daily, Display World, Retail Management, Lighting & Lamps, Glass Digest, and Handbags Illustrated are represented. The majority of the publicity here is for Silver & Co.'s midwestern jobs: Saks Fifth Avenue and the Rollins Company in Detroit, Kaufman's in Colorado Springs, and Woolf Brothers in Wichita and Kansas City. Scrapbook Two spans the time period from 1943 to 1956 and contains many newspaper clippings laid in. Silver & Co. ads that appeared in the New York Times are pasted onto pages. The majority of jobs represented here are from the 1950s, such as Bergdorf Goodman and the John B. Stetson Company. A 1955 booklet put out by Silver & Co. called "Business Interiors: office, store, showroom" is also pasted in. It contains about twenty pages of illustrations and decorating tips, and was sent to potential clients.
  - Scrapbook 1, 1931-1952 (Offsite-box 14, Folder unknown container)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1943-1956 (Offsite-box 15, Folder unknown container)
- Oversize Material
  - From Series I. Commercial Interiors
    - Three empty binders (Box 16, Folder unknown container)